A Guide to the Roger Pattrell Bristol Papers 1953-1976
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Roger Pattrell Bristol, 1953-1976
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
9516-d
This collection consists of 225 items, 1953-1986, and contains the correspondence and papers of the former Engineering Librarian at the University of Virginia's School of Engineering and Applied Science.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was made a gift to the Library by Mrs. Roger P. Bristol of Cockeysville, Maryland, on September 3, 1986.
Biographical/Historical Information
Roger P. Bristol was born on July 15, 1903, in Ascutney, Vermont. He received his B.A. (1923) and M.A. (1926) degrees in English at Boston University; and later received his M.L.S. (1949) from Simmons College. Prior to accepting the position of Head of the Preparations Division at Alderman Library in 1954, he served at Peabody Institute, and was the head cataloger at the Boston Public Library from 1947-1949. Bristol was responsible for many library systems improvements, especially in the addition of modern equipment. He researched the use of a closed-circuit television system in a decentralized library situation. He wrote numerous books, essays, and monographs on early American imprints as well as the vast Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography. During his last ten years at the University, he served as Engineering Librarian in the School of Engineering where he directed a program which resulted in a significant expansion of facilities and services.
Scope and Content Information
This group of personal papers and correspondence of the former Engineering Librarian at the University of Virginia's School of Engineering and Applied Science consists of 225 items in the period 1953-1976. The correspondence covers Bristol's career at the University, his involvement in the modernization of library systems, library mechanization, and his work on the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography and the reprint of its Index. The material in the topical series is chiefly concerned with the Supplement, and includes Bristol's working copy, and book reviews and other related printed material.
Correspondence with Jack Preston Dalton and John Cook Wyllie of Alderman Library details how Bristol first came to the University for an interview and eventually accepted the position as Head of the Preparations Division in 1954. There is also correspondence from Bristol's tenure as Engineering Librarian. During 1966-1973, Bristol orresponded with the American Antiquarian Society and the Bibliographical Society of America concerning the publication of his Supplement to Charles Evans'American Bibliography. Correspondence with Walker Cowen, Frederick R. Goff, John B. Hench, Marcus A. McCorison, Linton R. Massey, and James E. Mooney refers to negotiations and compromises made between the author, publisher, and printer.
Roger P. Bristol was born on July 15, 1903, in Ascutney, Vermont. He received his B.A. (1923) and M.A. (1926) degrees in English at Boston University; and later received his M.L.S. (1949) from Simmons College. Prior to accepting the position of Head of the Preparations Division at Alderman Library in 1954, he served at Peabody Institute, and was the head cataloger at the Boston Public Library from 1947-1949. Bristol was responsible for many library systems improvements, especially in the addition of modern equipment. He researched the use of a closed-circuit television system in a decentralized library situation. He wrote numerous books, essays, and monographs on early American imprints as well as the vast Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography. During his last ten years at the University, he served as Engineering Librarian in the School of Engineering where he directed a program which resulted in a significant expansion of facilities and services.
Contents List
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol concerning his career at the University of Virginia 1953-1976, 35 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol with IBM Corporation re library mechanization, and related publications 1963-1964, 10 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol re the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography 1966-1968, 63 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol with Peter Smith, publisher, re reprinting the Index to the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography1966, 5 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol re the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography 1969-1973, 41 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of Roger P. Bristol with Forrest Bowe and James E. Mooney, re Bowe's subject bibliography of French literature in early American translation 1970, 41 items (Box 1)
- American Bibliographical Notes, by Roger P. Bristol, reprinted from the Proceedings of the American Antiquarian Society 1972-1973, 4 items (Box 1)
- Bibliographical Society of the University of Virginia Secretary's News Sheet, listing "not-in-Evans" titles 1955-1967, 8 items (Box 1)
- Book Review of the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography, by Roger P. Bristol 1971, 8 items (Box 1)
- Evans American Bibliography: Supplement(Checking Edition), by Roger P. Bristol, with autograph changes, p. 1-224 and p. 225-638 1962, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Maryland Imprints 1801-1810, by Roger P. Bristol 1953, 1 item (Box 2)
- Printed material concerning the Supplement to Charles Evans' American Bibliography, by Roger P. Bristol 1972-1973, 2 items (Box 2)
- "Reports on Closed-Circuit TV in a Decentralized Library Situation" by Roger P. Bristol and related printed material 1957-1968, 14 items (Box 2)